Let's understand how to manage the Google Cloud infrastructure
without ever clicking a button in the console,
we call this the GitOps,
and we're going to use the Google Cloud config controller.
Let's first understand how this entire flow looks like.
So user will going to push a YAML file into the GitHub.
We have the config sync that detects the changes. And it will pull the
YAML file from the Git, we have the config connector.
The config connector converts this YAML file into the
corresponding Google Cloud API calls, and then the Google Cloud
received the request. And according to the request, it is going
to make the update into the resources.
Now let's just see how we can do that.
Behind the scenes,
I've already provisioned our management hub by running
gcloud and the config controller.
You can see that our config controller is already running.
That is a dedicated hidden GKE cluster.
The command to create this controller is like this.
Now I have already assigned this controller the owner
permission at the project level.
This allows our hub to talk to the Google APIs and
create the resource on our behalf.
You can see that we have here root‑sync.yaml.
Now in this root‑sync.yaml, we are providing our GitHub repository,
and I have already generated the token from my GitHub. You can also
generate the token from a GitHub by just coming down here,
going to the Settings tab, and in the bottom,
go to the Developer settings,
and you can generate a new personal access token from here.
Now you provide that Git credential,
so you can run this kubectl create secret generic git‑creds
command by providing your username and the token.
Now once you make those changes and apply it using kubectl apply ‑f
root‑sync.yaml, this is going to apply all those changes. And now your
config controller is in sync with your GitHub repository.
Now, once you have done that, let's go down to your GitHub.
Now into my GitHub repository, I have created a folder config,
and under that I have a YAML, bucket YAML that looks
like a standard Kubernetes manifest, but the kind is a storage bucket.
Now here you can see that I'm making one change, and I'm saying
that the bucket name which I'm now looking for is ‑2. And the
moment I'm going to commit these changes,
automatically it will start deploying this specific
bucket into our Google Cloud.
I say Commit changes.
And if I go down to here in our Google Cloud,
search for Buckets, right now you can see that earlier the bucket was 2025‑1.
Let's refresh,
and in the next few minutes, you will see that it has
deleted this specific bucket and created a new one
because it wants this to be in sync.
Now here you can see that it has created another bucket and deleted the
older one because I have changed that specific YAML file.
So that's how the config controller can help you to do the
GitOps without touching your Google console.